<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.0.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-07-14T16:44:08-04:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Adamalthus</title><subtitle>Technology ~ Policy ~ Economics</subtitle><entry><title>Beyond Cloud - The 3rd Computing Era</title><link href="/blog/2015/05/09/beyond-cloud-the-3rd-era/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Cloud - The 3rd Computing Era" /><published>2015-05-09T04:44:14-04:00</published><updated>2015-05-09T04:44:14-04:00</updated><id>1138</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/05/09/beyond-cloud-the-3rd-era/">Over the last couple of weeks I&#39;ve presented a more forward looking view of what lies beyond our current conception of cloud computing at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/The-3rd-Era-Enabling-A-Composable-Future-Final.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CloudConnect in Las Vegas&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/Beyond-Cloud.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research symposium at UC Berkeley&lt;/a&gt; and to the Northern California chapter of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/Beyond-Cloud1.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Young Presidents Organization&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve used these presentations to outline an evolving set of ideas anchored around the idea that we&#39;re in the middle of the 2nd Era of Computing rapidly evolving towards the 3rd Era. The organizing principle behind the &#39;Era&#39; concept is the degree of coupling in and between application code and the underlying infrastructure.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

During the 1st Era of Computing applications were tightly coupled to underlying hardware in order to optimize the use of scarce and expensive computing resources. The 2nd Era in which we now find ourselves requires loosely coupled architectures to enable resilient, elastic and composable, cloud scale application and service workloads. However, the coming data volume and management demands of trillions of connected devices - the Internet of Things - combined with the need for truly friction free machine-2-machine transactions will rapidly drive the emergence of the 3rd Era of Computing. In the 3rd Era we will move from loosely coupled of truly uncoupled architectures where code is free to execute when and where it is needed enabled by a new fabric of trusted, frictionless, smart contract based transactions.</content><author><name>JM</name></author><summary>Over the last couple of weeks I’ve presented a more forward looking view of what lies beyond our current conception of cloud computing at CloudConnect in Las Vegas, a research symposium at UC Berkeley and to the Northern California chapter of the Young Presidents Organization. I’ve used these presentations to outline an evolving set of ideas anchored around the idea that we’re in the middle of the 2nd Era of Computing rapidly evolving towards the 3rd Era. The organizing principle behind the ‘Era’ concept is the degree of coupling in and between application code and the underlying infrastructure.</summary></entry><entry><title>ILO Presentation: Enabling the ‘Composable Enterprise’™</title><link href="/blog/2015/04/02/ilo-presentation-enabling-the-composable-enterprise/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ILO Presentation: Enabling the &#39;Composable Enterprise&#39;&amp;trade;" /><published>2015-04-02T11:52:14-04:00</published><updated>2015-04-02T11:52:14-04:00</updated><id>1093</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/04/02/ilo-presentation-enabling-the-composable-enterprise/">&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linkedin.com/pub/peter-temes/2/588/170/en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Peter Temes&lt;/a&gt; - Founder and President of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iloinstitute.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Institute for Innovation in Large Organizations (ILO)&lt;/a&gt; - was kind enough to invite me to speak on enabling the &#39;[Composable Enterprise](http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2013/04/04/the-composable-enterprise/ &quot;The Composable Enterprise™&quot;)&#39;&amp;trade; at a recent meeting of the institute&#39;s members in New York.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt; A PDF of the presentation can found 

&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Enabling-The-Composable-Enterprise-ILO.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Peter has put together a stellar program with an &#39;A list&#39; corporate membership. The discussions at these events are always fascinating and informative. The discussion that followed last week&#39;s presentation got into some very interesting topics such as ethics of automation, an important topic indeed.</content><author><name>JM</name></author><summary>Peter Temes - Founder and President of the Institute for Innovation in Large Organizations (ILO) - was kind enough to invite me to speak on enabling the ‘Composable Enterprise‘™ at a recent meeting of the institute’s members in New York.</summary></entry><entry><title>Sharing in the Success of the Digital Economy</title><link href="/blog/2015/03/30/sharing-in-the-success-of-the-digital-economy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sharing in the Success of the Digital Economy" /><published>2015-03-30T13:08:45-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-30T13:08:45-04:00</updated><id>1068</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/03/30/sharing-in-the-success-of-the-digital-economy/">[Sharing in the success of the digital economy](http://www.policy-network.net/publications/4876/Sharing-in-the-Success-of-the-Digital-Economy)

&quot;The digitally enabled economy is unleashing a new wave of change, something we are only just beginning to feel and understand. The economic evidence shows that this innovation -the development and adoption of new products, services, processes and business models - is vital to support rising living standards. But making the political case for the progressive power of innovation, and the digital economy, can be more challenging. The forces of &#39;creative destruction&#39; threaten incumbent firms, jobs, and the way people work and live, creating strong incentives to oppose change. &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;Confronting these hard realities is one of the defining challenges for progressive politics in the 21&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;century.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;p1&quot;&gt;
  Includes a chapter by Desiree van Welsum and me.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>JM</name></author><summary>Sharing in the success of the digital economy

“The digitally enabled economy is unleashing a new wave of change, something we are only just beginning to feel and understand. The economic evidence shows that this innovation -the development and adoption of new products, services, processes and business models - is vital to support rising living standards. But making the political case for the progressive power of innovation, and the digital economy, can be more challenging. The forces of ‘creative destruction’ threaten incumbent firms, jobs, and the way people work and live, creating strong incentives to oppose change. Confronting these hard realities is one of the defining challenges for progressive politics in the 21st century.”


  Includes a chapter by Desiree van Welsum and me.</summary></entry><entry><title>The Industrialization of IT</title><link href="/blog/2015/03/18/cloud-computing-as-the-industrialization-of-it/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Industrialization of IT" /><published>2015-03-18T11:22:56-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-18T11:22:56-04:00</updated><id>1032</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/03/18/cloud-computing-as-the-industrialization-of-it/">Anyone who has spent any time discussing cloud with me, or seen me present on cloud issues will no doubt quickly learn how fond I am of analogizing this technology domain with the automotive industry.

Our drive to solve the Time-to-Value problem and to implement continuous value delivery have deep rooted connections to the mass production innovations of Ford, the scientific management disciplines of Taylor and the far reaching Lean Production System invented by Toyota. As IT professionals we have - in my view - much to learn from the rich industrial heritage of high volume manufacturing processes.

I recently had the opportunity to share my views on cloud computing and it&#39;s implications for developing economies at the World Bank in DC. Preparing for this talk gave me the opportunity to crystalize my thinking on the Cloud-Manufacturing analogy and are synthesized in the slides I presented which can be downloaded &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/Cloud-and-Industrialization-of-IT-Final.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.</content><author><name>JM</name></author><summary>Anyone who has spent any time discussing cloud with me, or seen me present on cloud issues will no doubt quickly learn how fond I am of analogizing this technology domain with the automotive industry.

Our drive to solve the Time-to-Value problem and to implement continuous value delivery have deep rooted connections to the mass production innovations of Ford, the scientific management disciplines of Taylor and the far reaching Lean Production System invented by Toyota. As IT professionals we have - in my view - much to learn from the rich industrial heritage of high volume manufacturing processes.

I recently had the opportunity to share my views on cloud computing and it’s implications for developing economies at the World Bank in DC. Preparing for this talk gave me the opportunity to crystalize my thinking on the Cloud-Manufacturing analogy and are synthesized in the slides I presented which can be downloaded here.</summary></entry><entry><title>Cloud Computing: From Scarcity to Abundance</title><link href="/blog/2015/02/18/cloud-computing-from-scarcity-to-abundance-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloud Computing: From Scarcity to Abundance" /><published>2015-02-18T11:53:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-02-18T11:53:00-05:00</updated><id>1021</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/02/18/cloud-computing-from-scarcity-to-abundance-2/">&lt;span style=&quot;color: #333333; font-family: Georgia, &#39;Times New Roman&#39;, &#39;Bitstream Charter&#39;, Times, serif; font-size: 16px; line-height: 24px;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Our &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10842-014-0188-y&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;latest paper&lt;/a&gt; on cloud computing and associated economic and policy implications was just published in the Journal of Industry, Trade and Competitiveness. Many thanks to my co-authors, Kenji Kushida and John Zysman.&lt;/span&gt;</content><author><name>JM</name></author><summary>Our latest paper on cloud computing and associated economic and policy implications was just published in the Journal of Industry, Trade and Competitiveness. Many thanks to my co-authors, Kenji Kushida and John Zysman.</summary></entry><entry><title>Inflection Points</title><link href="/blog/2015/02/05/inflection-points/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflection Points" /><published>2015-02-04T19:26:15-05:00</published><updated>2015-02-04T19:26:15-05:00</updated><id>1003</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/02/05/inflection-points/">Although the articles on &lt;a href=&quot;http://adamalathus.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;adamalthus.com&lt;/a&gt; represent my personal views on the intersection of technology, policy and economics I rarely write about the personal impact of these issues on me. That will be unavoidable with this posting. We sit at the inflection point between two eras of computing: The distributed machine and application focused model of today and the data driven composable service model of the &#39;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Metaform&lt;/a&gt;&#39; that is now emerging. The profound implications of this technical inflection have created a personal and professional inflection point. It&#39;s time to embark on a new journey&amp;hellip;&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

Over the last three years - working at Warner Music Group - I put together and then benefited from working with a very talented team of leaders, software engineers, user experience designers and process and product managers. This team - along with our rocket scientist development partners &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dataart.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DataArt&lt;/a&gt; - took a blank sheet of paper, a few ideas about a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2013/04/04/the-composable-enterprise/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Composable Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&amp;trade; and in a very short time birthed a revolutionary, open source, infrastructure agnostic, application and service platform that today runs important production workloads for the company. The combination of composable development model, aggressively agile processes and a purpose built software factory platform has already delivered substantial and quantifiable improvements in &#39;Time-to-Value.&#39;

My experience at Warner Music has further reinforced my belief that enterprise software development has to evolve in the direction I outlined in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2013/04/04/the-composable-enterprise/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Composable Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&amp;trade;. The speed, dynamics of competition and uncertainty in today&#39;s business environment make the old model of large scale monolithic application development - with value delivered in huge chunks every eighteen months - irrelevant. I can think of few - if any - business, market, service or product strategies - that aren&#39;t entirely dependent an effective efficient and agile technology foundation. Without that you&#39;re business will be - at best - irrelevant or dead.

Over recent months I&#39;ve come to realize that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Metaform&lt;/a&gt; will be the true enabler of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2013/04/04/the-composable-enterprise/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Composable Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&amp;trade;. A platform that exposes the widest range of business functions and data sources through well defined and trusted interfaces will empower the next generation entrepreneurs and forward thinking business leaders. New services and businesses themselves will be &#39;composed&#39; out of the component services and data of other businesses - all made accessible and consumable by the Metaform.

The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Metaform&lt;/a&gt; will create a market for the component functions and services from which other services and businesses can be built or evolved. Particpating in this market will require an level of technology agility that today few enterprises possess. The emergence of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Metaform&lt;/a&gt; opportunity creates an yet another unavoidable imperative for enterprise IT to evolve.

Recognizing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Metaform&lt;/a&gt; inflection point reinforced my view that the model we built at Warner Music and the set of ideas embodied in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2013/04/04/the-composable-enterprise/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Composable Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&amp;trade; are likely to become mainstream. As that happens we will witness a generational shift in the enterprise computing landscape and with that, growing demand for the platforms, tooling and processes that enable that change. I left Warner Music at the end 2014 to pursue that opportunity.

For now there are two parts to my new adventure. The newly founded &lt;a href=&quot;http://innoviastrategies.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Innovia Strategies&lt;/a&gt; firm will focus on providing advisory services to leaders looking to solve the &#39;Time-to-Value&#39; problem. Our goal is to help leaders understand and then develop, business, organizational and technology strategies to position themselves to take advantage of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Metaform&lt;/a&gt; opportunity.

The second part of the puzzle is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://nflexn.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;n.flex.n&lt;/a&gt;. There&#39;s not much more I can say about this project except that &quot;When Time-to-Value _really_ matters, n.flex.n delivers.&quot; Make sure you sign up and you&#39;ll be amongst the first to hear about it when we launch.

I&#39;m pretty confident that a seismic shift in computing model is about to take place that will transform not only enterprise computing but computing as it affects us all. So without the benefit of pre-cognition I&#39;m willing to bank on there being opportunity in this tectonic shift. I have little real idea of where this path will eventually take me but I&#39;m ready to enjoy the journey.</content><author><name>JM</name></author><summary>Although the articles on adamalthus.com represent my personal views on the intersection of technology, policy and economics I rarely write about the personal impact of these issues on me. That will be unavoidable with this posting. We sit at the inflection point between two eras of computing: The distributed machine and application focused model of today and the data driven composable service model of the ‘Metaform’ that is now emerging. The profound implications of this technical inflection have created a personal and professional inflection point. It’s time to embark on a new journey…</summary></entry><entry><title>The ‘Metaform’ - The Platform of Everything</title><link href="/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘Metaform&#39; - The Platform of Everything" /><published>2015-01-07T19:01:16-05:00</published><updated>2015-01-07T19:01:16-05:00</updated><id>992</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/01/08/the-metaform-the-platform-of-everything/">We are witnessing a period of unparalleled digital service innovation where new services are increasingly built by wiring together the business capabilities of multiple other firms exposed through open cloud based service interfaces.

Welcome to the era of the &#39;Metaform&#39; - The Platform of Everything.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

In software a ‘Platform&#39; is an integrated set of technologies accessible through standardized application programming interfaces (APIs) upon which new software applications and services can be built.

The economic potential of a platform results from the breadth and depth of functionality encapsulated by the platform, how accessible the platform is to developers and consumers.

As software platforms have evolved they have become increasingly abstracted from the underlying infrastructures on which they run. As a result modern software platforms have evolved away from merely exposing low level hardware and network functions towards higher levels of business capability.

Firms routinely today expose their business processes and functions to the outside world via APIs. UPS and Fedex do this to enable other firms to integrate with their logistics services. In a very real sense business processes and even whole businesses are becoming digital service platforms.

New startups such as [Shyp] use the platforms of other logistics firms to build their own higher level service offerings. In Shyp&#39;s case they offer on-demand pickup, packing and shipping of goods for consumers.

The travel booking service [Trivago] is built on top of the platforms of other travel services such as Expedia, Orbitz and others to offer consumers the ability to search for the best travel offers without visiting each individual website.

We are now entering the era of the ‘Meta&#39; platform - the ‘Metaform&#39; - where a new generation of startups increasingly construct new services by composing together the digital business functions and processes of other firms.

There will be unimaginable opportunity for new service innovation in a world where the core business functions and capabilities of the widest range of businesses across all industrial sectors are available as building blocks to be wired together in new and interesting ways.

On the other side of the balance sheet the ‘Metaform&#39; is going to provide companies with a way to unlock the value of their existing internal capabilities by exposing them to demand from the outside world.

There are substantial issues to overcome to realize the full potential of ‘Metaform&#39; not the least of which includes: working out how to automate and streamline the payment and contractual terms between component service providers and protecting consumer data as it flows through the systems of multiple independent entities. But, the enormity of the global opportunity for a new wave of digital service innovation is likely to see these issues resolved.

Companies such as Shyp, Trivago and others are pioneers of the &#39;Metaform&#39; opportunity but they are but early indicators of a very profound transformation of the digital services economy and a tidal wave of service innovation we&#39;re about to witness in the years ahead.</content><author><name>JM</name></author><summary>We are witnessing a period of unparalleled digital service innovation where new services are increasingly built by wiring together the business capabilities of multiple other firms exposed through open cloud based service interfaces.

Welcome to the era of the ‘Metaform’ - The Platform of Everything.</summary></entry><entry><title>Cloud Computing’s Free Lunch</title><link href="/blog/2014/10/23/the-free-lunch-is-coming-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloud Computing&#39;s Free Lunch" /><published>2014-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2014/10/23/the-free-lunch-is-coming-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2014/10/23/the-free-lunch-is-coming-2/">One of my mother&#39;s favortite sayings is &quot;There&#39;s no such thing as a free lunch&quot; Generally that&#39;s a pretty good rule to live buy. If it looks like your being offered something for nothing then take a second look. You&#39;ll almost always end up paying somewhere down the line. However, when it comes to cloud computing a ‘Free Lunch&#39; may become a very real possibility.

Amazon, Microsoft and Google are engaged in a battle for market share and customer loyalty which has seen the price of basic computing resources decline preciptously over recent years. Therein lies the free lunch. However, each of them expects to monetize this growing customers base buy charging for higher level services. There&#39;s the rub. Maximizing the free lunch oportunity will require smart customers to figure out how to dine inexpensively while limiting consumption of that expensive bottle of wine.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

The price of the basic components of computing - CPU, disk storage and memory - as delieverd by the major cloud providers such as Amazon, Microsoft and Google - has had a tremendous downard trajectory. Amazon trumpets the fact that its most recent instance price decreases were its &lt;a title=&quot;&quot; href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/aws-price-reduction-42-ec2-s3-rds-elasticache-and-elastic-mapreduce/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;42nd such reduction since 2008&lt;/a&gt;. Microsoft and Google have continued to match Amazon&#39;s pricing declines.

The ongoing decline in the price of the raw materials of cloud computing shows no signs of slowing down which leaves one to draw the conclusion that - within some reasonable time horizon - the price will approximate zero - or as close as makes no difference. Clearly not even the global scale economics of Amazon, Microsoft or Google enable you to give away computing for free, so what&#39;s going on?

My &lt;a title=&quot;&quot; href=&quot;http://www.adamalthus.com/blog/2013/04/01/the-laws-of-platform-economics/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;First Law of Platform Economics&lt;/a&gt; states that &quot;Value alway moves up the stack&quot; IE. It is always the case that the lower layers of any generation of platform archiecture eventually become comoditized and therefore value tends to be extracted by monetizing services higher and higher in the stack over time. Once upon a time you could make money selling operating systems, then databases and then line-of-business applications. This was the trajectory of the last ‘client-server&#39; wave of technology. Cloud is no different.

It&#39;s very likely that the three behemoths of the global cloud ecosystem are using thier scale to drive pricing of the raw materials to zero. This is to their significant advantage as it creates a huge pricing barrier to entry for smaller less-scaled players. Being able to amortize very sizeable capital investments and operational costs over a rapidly growing customer base helps them. Forgoeing margins - profitability - to secure maket share and a growing subscriber base is exactly the right strategy now but ultimately it will need to be supplanted by a strategy which extracts value from those captured customers.

This - admitedly somewhat dated - &lt;a title=&quot;&quot; href=&quot;http://research.gigaom.com/report/amazon-web-services-by-the-numbers/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;set of charts from GigaOm&lt;/a&gt; paints a very clear picture of how Amazon see thier strategy unfolding. In short Amazon are giving away the raw materials beacuse they&#39;re betting that eventually customers will pay for higher level services - value always moves up the stack.

The set of services Amazon are building out include data and media processing pipelines, analytics services and the like. At some point it would not be surprinsing to see them offer what we would think of today as full line-of-business solutions. The strategy from Google, Microsoft and others is likely to be no different. So what is it going to take to maximize this opportunity?

Customers wanting to take advantage of ongoing declines in computing resource pricing - while avoiding the expense of higher level services - require a strategy that lets them consume raw computing resources at an ever declining cost while insulating themselves from the need to buy into costly higher level services.

The default choice for most organizations will be to build new cloud based applications ‘Natively&#39; on a specific cloud providers fabric. On the surface this strategy is appealing but has the significant disavantage of binding workloads directly to API&#39;s native to that fabric. In effect customers would end up merely substituting one set of - legacy - vendor dependecies with another. Once built natively the lifecycle costs of managing these new workloads will be bound to the cloud vendors unique monetization strategy.

A ‘Free lunch&#39; strategy requires the ability to decouple new cloud based application workloads from dependence on any one infrastructure vendor. This approach requires customers to take control of the platform layer between applictaions and the underlying infrastructure. The decoupling afforded by a new generation of Platform as a Service (PaaS) offerings such as Cloud Foundry is a good starting point.

Building on top of a service platform which is decoupled from the underlying infrastructure will enable customers to keep control of thier own destiny. Every organization will need to make an appropriate economic analysis of this new buy vs. build dynamic. But there&#39;s no escaping the imperative for cloud infrastructure vendors to evenutally monetize higher level services to pay for the raw materials they are giving away for free.

Customer&#39;s whose strategies maximize choice and reduce thier dependence on any one specific cloud provider&#39;s offerings will be best positioned to take advantage of what is likley to become a free lunch opportunity.</content><summary>One of my mother’s favortite sayings is “There’s no such thing as a free lunch” Generally that’s a pretty good rule to live buy. If it looks like your being offered something for nothing then take a second look. You’ll almost always end up paying somewhere down the line. However, when it comes to cloud computing a ‘Free Lunch’ may become a very real possibility.

Amazon, Microsoft and Google are engaged in a battle for market share and customer loyalty which has seen the price of basic computing resources decline preciptously over recent years. Therein lies the free lunch. However, each of them expects to monetize this growing customers base buy charging for higher level services. There’s the rub. Maximizing the free lunch oportunity will require smart customers to figure out how to dine inexpensively while limiting consumption of that expensive bottle of wine.</summary></entry><entry><title>Technology’s Triple Threat</title><link href="/blog/2014/10/05/technologys-triple-threat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology&#39;s Triple Threat" /><published>2014-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2014/10/05/technologys-triple-threat</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2014/10/05/technologys-triple-threat/">#### Cross-posted from the Innovia Ventures Blog by Jonathan Murray &amp; Desiree van Welsum

What impact will the increasingly widespread use of digital tools and information have on our society and economy and how will we deal with the disruptive forces brought to life and amplified by these technologies?

Understanding the nature of this emerging transformation and identifying appropriate responses to ensure we successfully navigate the challenges is critical. Without this we risk a level of social and economic dislocation unseen since our transition to an industrial economy in the 17th and 18th centuries. But whereas the transition from an agricultural to an industrial economy took over one hundred years, the transition from industrial to a cyber-economy will likely take a few decades at most - a rate of change our political and social systems are ill-prepared to deal with.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

The impact of social media and digital communications tools on the political landscape is increasingly well understood. There is an emerging and very active discourse about the transformation of the labor force by digital automation and the impact on skills and training. The role of digital tools and access to information in driving increased inequality and asymmetric wealth distribution is also recognized if not fully illuminated in active political debate. What is not well understood is how each of these points of social and economic pressure are interconnected - in effect each of these factors is one component of a self-reinforcing system powered and driven forward with increasing momentum by &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore&#39;s_law&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moore&#39;s law&lt;/a&gt;.

Finding a way through the maze of challenges facing us requires a system-wide view of the impacts of digital tools and technologies and their interrelationship. This is not a problem that will be solved in pieces.

The &#39;Triple-Threat&#39; framework outlined here is offered as a starting point for a more integrated debate about the ramifications of the coming digital transformation. This approach draws together the three primary stress-points caused by increased adoption and use of digital technology across our society and economy: Wealth inequality, Labor market disruption and Social communication. The nature of each of these digitally driven stress-points can be summarized as follows.

#### Wealth Inequality

Technology creates great wealth, but it tends to accrue to relatively few people - what Erik Brynjolfsson and Andrew McAfee refer to as &#39;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2011/10/why-workers-are-losing-the-war-against-machines/247278/?single_page=true&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;superstar biased technological change&lt;/a&gt;&#39;. Examples include the founders of successful tech companies such as Facebook, Twitter and Airbnb which amass multi-billion dollar valuations but have created relatively few jobs. Nor is that wealth shared with the various agents - Uber drivers, AirBnB property owners etc. &amp;mdash; who helped build the successful companies commanding those valuations.

Increasingly sophisticated use of computational tools and resources across the finance industry has lead to accelerated returns on capital vastly outpacing returns on invested labor. Financial institutions can afford the capital expenditures necessary to enable ever more computationally intense derivative modelling which expands the market for financial products.

The ability of wealth to ensure access to higher quality education and early access to digital technology in the home creates a self-reinforcing digital &#39;divide&#39;. Children brought up with access to wealth have a differential advantage in exploiting digital tools and information to generate economic returns that outstrip those without those inbuilt advantages.

#### Labor Disruption

Technology has traditionally replaced jobs through automation, and created new jobs elsewhere. However, with recent technological progress, the scope for the hollowing out of not only blue collar but also white collar/knowledge worker jobs has dramatically increased and has created much anxiety over job destruction.

The jury is still very much out over whether or not the economy will be able to create sufficient new jobs to make up for the ones being displaced. The nay-sayers are hiding from a reality where companies will try to replace workers with software wherever they can (unless a major cultural change is brought about in how companies view and treat their human resources). Going forward, in figuring out what humans will end up doing, finding the complementarities between tasks computers can do better and those where humans still have a comparative advantage will be key.

A new round of manufacturing labor dynamics is already at play with manufacturing leaving developing economies and being substituted for by highly automated manufacturing capacity in developed economies closer to consumers. As manufacturing moves back to developed economies the jobs are unlikely to follow - at least in comparison to those being displaced.

Who is going to take responsibility for skilling the workforce? The structure of the k-12 education system in most developed countries is still based on the needs of an industrial economy and workforce. Educational systems move far too slowly to respond to rapid structural changes brought on by technology.

The &#39;contract&#39; between employers and the employed has broken down. Jobs are no longer for life and as a result businesses are reluctant to invest in long-term employee skill development. Workers are reluctant to invest in their own skill development because of the uncertain returns.

Google&#39;s CEO Larry Page recently posited that in the future all work will be &lt;a href=&quot;http://recode.net/2014/07/05/the-future-of-the-workforce-may-be-part-time-says-google-ceo-larry-page/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;part-time&lt;/a&gt;. That may be so but unless those part-time jobs provide a living wage then workers are likely to be highly dissatisfied with that outcome.

#### Social &amp; Mass Communication

The &#39;double edged&#39; nature of the evolving impact of technology on our societies can be most clearly seen in the domain of mass and social communications. An arms race is currently underway between those in power and those that seek to undermine that power. The &#39;Arab Spring&#39; uprisings across the Middle East clearly demonstrated the organizing power of today&#39;s social communications tools but also their limitations. Meanwhile new social communication tools and can be deployed as asymmetric networks of mass influence for those in power of for the &quot;loudest&quot; most well financed voices.

The technologically savvy, well informed and well-financed have an even more powerful tool now to influence the masses. At the same time, communication technologies also provide tools for individuals to get organized. For example, with companies increasingly using contract and part-time workers, unionization or other means of protecting workers through traditional channels have been eroded. However, these individual workers now also have the ability to self-organize using mobile social communication technologies, creating a stronger voice and more bargaining power.

It should be a source of concern that people appear to be increasingly disenfranchised not only from the businesses that employ them, but also from the political structures and governments that ultimate only functional well with their participation. Falling voter turnout across developed economies speaks to a growing dissatisfaction with the political class and a growing gulf between them and the citizens they serve. An increasingly disaffected and disenfranchised citizenry is likely to co-opt social communication tools and networks to wrest control back from those perceived as not understanding their needs or acting in their best interests.

It is already apparent that less-democratically inclined governments are investing significantly in the technological tools required to control this growing digital conversation. China continues to demonstrated a very sophisticated ability to control the flow of information and political debate within its borders. The ability of democratic regimes to find the appropriate balance between control of these new communication channels and protected freedoms of expression will be more challenging and the prescription less obvious. The growing use of these communication tools by external threats to our democratic systems is already raising serious political debate about the level of control and inspection citizens will accept.

#### An Integrated Threat

In isolation each of the technologically driven challenges - Wealth Inequality, Labor disruption and Social and mass communications - pose a significant threat to existing economic and social order. But none of these factors operates in isolation. They can all be viewed as parts of a self-reinforcing system.

Individuals or firms with capital can buy outsized influence over populations through the use of new social and digital mass communications tools. Capital rich firms are able to use their wealth to support an investment cycle of ever greater automation that increasingly displaces labor. A citizenry increasingly under stress from labor market disruptions and growing inequalities will use social communications tools and networks to self-organize in an attempt to wrest or rebalance power from the wealthy and political classes.

Politicians and policy makers need to be aware that the digital future is not necessarily only rosy. It would be irresponsible to not acknowledge that the disruptive forces described in this article have the potential to seriously impact people&#39;s lives, and societies as a whole. An effective response will require an integrated approach, taking into account not just the individual drivers of the dislocation outlined but the means by which these drivers interact and reinforce each other.

An integrated approach to the &#39;Triple-Threat&#39; will require policy responses that span the width and depth of political structures, from education, social and labor departments to deal with the consequences of growing inequalities and labor disruptions, to justice and competition departments to deal with protecting people&#39;s &#39;digital lives&#39;, without impeding on the ability of businesses to innovate and continue to transform the way the economy operates. The benefits of making the economy more efficient should be shared.

Failing to address the dislocations brought on by an ever expanding digital transformation will have dire consequences. Unresolved, these disruptive forces may well lead to outcomes that are not sustainable, creating tremendous social and economic pain and yet further disruption.

Many observers point out that we have lived through similar transformative cycles in the past and in each case our societies, economies and political structures have adapted. That may well be true again but all of those previous transformations provided us with many decades and even centuries to adapt. We are not likely to have that luxury this time round. The pace of technological change and the speed with which those changes are impacting us will be measured in a few tens of years. Whatever the outcome that rapid pace of deep structural change is likely to be very painful to live through.

The transformation from agricultural to industrial based societies eventually led to far better outcomes for the citizenry but Charles Dickens still built a literary legacy based on documenting the squalor, deprivation and challenges of those forced to live through the transformation. However positive the outcome of the digital transformation we are now living through, the process of transformation is likely to be deeply challenging for many in our societies.</content><summary>Cross-posted from the Innovia Ventures Blog by Jonathan Murray &amp;amp; Desiree van Welsum

What impact will the increasingly widespread use of digital tools and information have on our society and economy and how will we deal with the disruptive forces brought to life and amplified by these technologies?

Understanding the nature of this emerging transformation and identifying appropriate responses to ensure we successfully navigate the challenges is critical. Without this we risk a level of social and economic dislocation unseen since our transition to an industrial economy in the 17th and 18th centuries. But whereas the transition from an agricultural to an industrial economy took over one hundred years, the transition from industrial to a cyber-economy will likely take a few decades at most - a rate of change our political and social systems are ill-prepared to deal with.</summary></entry><entry><title>Is there a ‘can’ in your future?</title><link href="/blog/2014/08/19/the-can-is-coming/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is there a &#39;can&#39; in your future?" /><published>2014-08-19T13:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-08-19T13:55:00-04:00</updated><id>926</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2014/08/19/the-can-is-coming/">In the economics of computing the most expensive resource is still the network. In scenarios where large data-sets are being processed it is almost always cheaper to move computation to the data than the other way round. My friend and former colleague Dave McCrory nicely captured this reality in his concept of &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.mccrory.me/2010/12/07/data-gravity-in-the-clouds/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Data Gravity&lt;/a&gt;.Today&#39;s cloud based computing architectures assume that _all_ data will flow to the center to be processed. Unfortunately, this centralized data-processing model is not likely to be economically viable as we look forward to a tsunami of data being generated by trillions of connected devices and sensors.

In the brave new world of the &#39;Internet of Things&#39; - IoT - moving every bit of generated data from edge devices to the center for processing will likely make little economic sense. A new distributed data processing architecture is going to be required.

Content Distribution Networks (CDNs) are a common way of efficiently moving data from the center to the edge of the network but a new generation of Content Aggregation Networks (CANs) may be required to make the processing of IoT data economically viable - is there a &#39;CAN&#39; in your future?&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

Content Distribution Networks - CDNs are frequently used to get data out to edge devices with the most efficiency and cost effectiveness. A CDN acts an efficient distribution network for data accessed by end users - html, css, scripts, audio, video etc. &amp;mdash; all the stuff that ends up being rendered by our browsers and media players. CDN&#39;s move large volumes of this data from the center out - through high capacity, low cost, pipes - to local &#39;Points-of-Presence&#39; which are geographically close to the end user. This model allows for economically efficient distribution while at the same time greatly improves the end user experience by reducing the time to serve individual user requests.

Overcoming the economic challenges of transferring huge volumes of IoT generated data are likely to need network distribution architectures that work like CDNs _in reverse_. In effect we&#39;re going to need a new generation of &#39;Content Aggregation Networks&#39; (CAN). A CAN will compliment a CDN by optimizing the flow of data from edge devices to cloud based processing in the center. But what sets that apart from standard networking technology and topologies that make up today&#39;s IP network? In two words: Computation and Filtering.

In an IoT connected world it will make little sense to move every bit of data generated by a sensor - or edge device - to the center for processing. The primary role of a CAN will be to distribute tiered computational processing and filters across the network including to the edge devices. Just like the supplier network of a large manufacturing company the CAN will ensure that data gets processed where it makes sense and only &#39;value-added&#39; bits are allowed to flow towards the center. In essence a CAN will enable architects to assign a relative economic value to each bit and only then allow those bits which justify the cost of transport to flow upstream.

In a CAN enabled architecture an environmental sensor might only send bits across the network when a detected signal crosses some % value above ambient. The CAN would be responsible for distributing the the computation and threshold filter algorithms to the sensors across the network. Even when threshold is crossed it might not make economic sense to flow data all the way to the center for processing. Instead the CAN would provision a data processing node close - an edge computing instance - to the sensor network so that aggregate sensor data can be locally analyzed. Only the analytic product from this local processing may eventually flow to the center.

Our current generation of &#39;Big Data&#39; processing infrastructures - such a Hadoop - use a distributed architecture where computation is distributed across a number of &#39;compute nodes&#39; which then act on local subsets of data. From one perspective a CAN could be thought of as a network wide version of the same architecture. However, a CAN would also be required to initiate edge computing instances on demand and to provide distributed cost modelling and filtering mechanisms to optimize the downstream flow of data towards the center in a cloud based computing environment.

The competitive landscape for CANs appears to be wide open at the moment but there&#39;s some indication that this will soon change. The major cloud service providers - Amazon, Google and Microsoft - are likely to see this as a major opportunity but the need to distribute computation to the edge of the network will challenge their existing infrastructure and business models.

The opportunity to move up the value chain with CANs is likely to be far too compelling for Cisco to let the opportunity pass them by. Cisco have been looking for a rational to exploit the distributed computational fabric of their router business for years. The CAN opportunity may be just the ticket.

The existing Hadoop and &#39;Big Data&#39; processing players are also likely candidates seeing CANs as a natural extension of their existing distributed data processing architectures but its difficult to see how any of them could reach the scale to be relevant unless in partnership with one of the big infrastructure players.

For the highly distributed computational CAN model to achieve global scale we&#39;re also going to need a set of standards. Will we see the emergence of a common - interoperable - standard for the distribution of computational algorithms, filters and cost models across highly distributed infrastructures - including to the most microscopic of end-point sensor nodes? I hope so, because without these standards and a new generation of CAN architectures - and in a world with a growing deluge of IoT data - economically sifting the signal from the noise is likely to be close to impossible.</content><author><name>Jonathan</name></author><summary>In the economics of computing the most expensive resource is still the network. In scenarios where large data-sets are being processed it is almost always cheaper to move computation to the data than the other way round. My friend and former colleague Dave McCrory nicely captured this reality in his concept of Data Gravity.Today’s cloud based computing architectures assume that all data will flow to the center to be processed. Unfortunately, this centralized data-processing model is not likely to be economically viable as we look forward to a tsunami of data being generated by trillions of connected devices and sensors.

In the brave new world of the ‘Internet of Things’ - IoT - moving every bit of generated data from edge devices to the center for processing will likely make little economic sense. A new distributed data processing architecture is going to be required.

Content Distribution Networks (CDNs) are a common way of efficiently moving data from the center to the edge of the network but a new generation of Content Aggregation Networks (CANs) may be required to make the processing of IoT data economically viable - is there a ‘CAN’ in your future?</summary></entry></feed>
